[SPEAKER_01]: Although living a virtuous, renunciate and secluded life, when I reflect about my day in the evenings, I feel like I have still been pushed around all day, despite not having failed in any of the aforementioned qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I stop being pushed around?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, assuming that the questioner here is pushed around by his own mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it's good, of course, to be established in virtue, but that's not going to be enough now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is just the first step.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, keeping eight precepts is step one, but there's a lot of room within those
[SPEAKER_00]: You still do all sorts of things that come out of your mind, pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to establish yourself in the basic precepts, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Five plus celibacy and the non-distraction, that is the starting point for any serious mental development.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yes, you can adhere to those precepts externally, but the point is then twofold.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the first point is that without establishing yourself in a precept, you're not even going to see your own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to set up that boundary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind will be running into it and that is where you can see, aha, I've been going in the wrong direction now and because I'm keeping these precepts, right, I've put up that fence and I'm determined to not go past it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where you see your mind pushing you in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can catch a glimpse that you have been running with your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are at the point of breaking the precepts, you're not breaking it, but that's so... that container of the precepts is necessary to even see what your mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's their aim.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the second step is that you just don't want to be keeping it like that, but you now want to take that principle of understanding what it means to be pressured by your own mind, and you want to make that the sole criteria for whether something is wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, every time you give in to the pressure of your mind, that is out of weakness on your part.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have to then realize that the mind, citta, cannot actually force you to act.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might feel like that, but you're always there with it, giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, out of carelessness, you can forget this right perspective and still go with the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not good.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, more importantly, we want to recognize, yeah, the mind cannot actually
[SPEAKER_00]: force me to do things, I am there with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is why we often speak about taking or discerning this attitude of full complete responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the whole thing is up to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, if you then externally keep the precepts, and you live a fairly secluded life, but at the end of the day you look back and you see, yeah, my mind was still bossing me around all day long, then that means that within the context of those precepts, you need to refine it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to look at your sensory strength, for example, like, which things am I attending through, eh, during my day, and just, eh, more generally,
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarify what is mind, what does it mean to be pressured by my own mind, and am I still giving into that because I think it's too painful if I don't, or am I recognizing, no, the training is to not give in to the pressure of the mind, and then to recognize when the mind is pressuring you, which could be about
[SPEAKER_00]: Something that is not at all covered by the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the beginning, it looks like, oof, it's a big challenge to even keep those eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, that's the starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: At some point, you'll recognize, okay, I'm fairly solid now in keeping those precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That that fence is getting more and more in the distance now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not running into the fence the whole time anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so, that's a good first step.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you want to take it
[SPEAKER_00]: More carefully, and want to look more closely, because what do those three steps cover?
[SPEAKER_00]: They cover your bodily behavior, and also your speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not lying, not any lewd speech, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the actual purification now needs to happen on the
[SPEAKER_00]: Mental level, what it is that you are thinking about, what it is that you accept and welcome and delight in mentally, or alternatively, all the things that you think shouldn't be there mentally and you want to get rid of, basically also hindrances, that's primarily on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is still the mind pressuring you there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you see, you're never gonna recognize any of that if the bodily and the verbal behavior is not restrained first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the first step.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah, if you purify the stream, let's say, at the top of the mountain, then it's impossible that it becomes contaminated further downstream.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... since we don't start in a neutral position, we first need to actually discern the whole origin of the stream, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why yoniso, manasikāra is also a necessary factor for the arising of the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that begins by restraining bodily and verbal behavior, so that you even begin to see what is citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: That which is pressuring you, as we talked about in the earlier discussion, and then you want to recognize that also on the mental level, on your, right, the thoughts that you welcome and delight in or want to get rid of, there too, citta is pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, there is also something as, let's say, mental discipline.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keeping an eye on the kinds of thoughts that you welcome and delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if they are sensual, you shouldn't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should not delight in those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cut them off.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're having entire conversations going on, that are rooted in annoyance, ill-will, aversion, why is this happening to me, self-pity, and all the rest of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can go on for a while and you cannot notice it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is... there's still pressure behind that, behind those mental actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, it can be somewhat of a discovery to realize, wait, there is such a thing as mental action.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can actually also just stop certain thoughts or at least not welcome and enlighten them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, I do have a responsibility also for what is going on mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is what you now want to
[SPEAKER_00]: Start looking into and developing, because if you do not welcome and delight anymore in thoughts of sensuality, if you do not welcome and delight ill-will, annoyance, thoughts of cruelty and so on, it's going to be impossible that by body and speech, anything of that kind is going to factually manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you tackle the problem there, right, you're moving, like, that whole fence is, like, properly in the distance now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, somebody can be established in virtue, by which I take it to mean he's just keeping the precepts externally, but to be accomplished in virtue, as the suttas often say, accomplished in virtue means that you are not just conforming to a set of rules externally, but you understand that what makes those rules
[SPEAKER_00]: Why those rules are there?
[SPEAKER_00]: What makes breaking them unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Namely, that breaking any of those precepts means that you were totally overpowered by the pressure of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible to break those rules otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so you want to understand the principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you see what makes something wholesome and unwholesome, which has nothing to do with what the world externally might think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Has nothing to do with even specific sets of rules that you adhere to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that comes out of you giving in to the pressure of your own mind is unwholesome, even if it's not covered by the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, understanding this principle means that whatever you do by body, speech and mind, you're gonna ask yourself, wait, why am I doing this now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I accepting, tolerating, going with this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, why am I resisting this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it mine that I ask for it, or is it just there?
[SPEAKER_00]: And so you begin to question your involvement with those phenomena, and see, wait, I'm also responsible for my attitudes, for what I welcome and delight in, and what I want to get rid of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you will go to experience more subtle manifestations of the same pressure, and the mind craving, that's what pressure is, and yeah, then mentally you shouldn't give in to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by not giving in to those things mentally, if that becomes the level of your practice now, then at the end of the day, you will not feel that you have been bossed around by your own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you haven't left any corners for your mind to be bossing you around, because you've now included that whole mental domain in your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you say it's useful trying to discern first this principle of actually referring your actions always to your mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, throughout the day, any physical action, any verbal action, you actually first and foremost, obviously, it's within the precepts, let's assume, you first and foremost always look at your mind state, if there's any potential of
[SPEAKER_01]: agitating the mind, if there's any potential that the mind pressures you towards it, even if it's something fairly wholesome, you could say, on the physical and verbal level, like studying, reading suttas, making a project, but you see the mind wants to do it, leaps towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And to actually pay attention to that tendency, because that's where, even within precepts, restraint and seclusion, the bossing around still happens.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, with everything that you are doing, you have to ask yourself, wait, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: And why am I doing it specifically now?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you can ask yourself, okay, what would happen if I'm not going to do it now?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, not so much like what are going to be the actual consequences on the world level.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is your mind going to make a dhamma about it if you don't do it now?
[SPEAKER_00]: If it does, and you will be able to feel it, like, oh yeah, this is going to be a bit annoying if I'm not going to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means that your mind is behind there, pressuring you to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when you should not do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you see, it doesn't then even matter what it is that you're effectively going to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not breaking any of the precepts, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, and in the beginning, it might look like that everything that you do is coming out of the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody hears, okay, mind is putting pressure on me, you take that message on, and then you realize, well, everything I do is coming out of pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that is just because the craving, the pressure, hasn't been discerned sufficiently accurately.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is the refinement that needs to happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, the mind will be pushing you in some specific direction and then, the more you recognize that and do not give in to that pressure, the more you will begin to realize that there's actually a lot of space around it for other things to do that do now not come out of that pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can't do those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're sort of parallel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind wants to pressure you this way, and you're just going to do something else that doesn't come out of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure is saying, I want you to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start doing something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meanwhile, keeping an eye on your mind, it still wants you to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on the one hand, you resist the direction in which your mind wants to pressure you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, which other thing you do, doesn't even matter all that much.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you also become less concerned with what am I going to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: The emphasis shifts to what am I not going to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you see, next day, the thing that the mind is pressuring you to do now,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you could perhaps do it, because now the mind is not behind it pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether something is right or wrong for you on a certain occasion, is not determined by any sort of external code or conduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's fully determined internally, by whether your mind is pushing you to do it, or whether you are in fact doing it, not out of weakness, because the mind is behind you, pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that means...
[SPEAKER_00]: But you see, in order to now find out if it is okay to do this or not, you obviously need to see your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that you're only going to see when you start with the virtue, the restraint and the seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the mind is not always putting pressure on you with the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this basically means that you have to be on the ball the whole time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the right mindfulness comes in.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right mindfulness is, if I'm not going to do what I want to do now, it's going to be an issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Issue in relation to, will the mind take it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it just going to be sort of, equanimous with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, okay, we can do it some other time, no big deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it going to be like, yeah, but I really want to do this sort of now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you need to be in that sense,
[SPEAKER_00]: More rational and say, well, this is not the right time to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: We might do it on some future occasion.
[SPEAKER_00]: We don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: We will see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, that is all part of the training.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you will also recognize how futile it is to think that you can just train for an hour in the morning and an hour in the evening, because this just has to concern everything that you do 24-7, whether you're alone or with others, whether it's day or night.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as a parent is responsible for the child, and you cannot say, I'm going to be responsible for my child only for one hour in the morning and one hour in the evening, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Either you say, I'm bound up with this child, I need to look after it, or else, you're not a responsible parent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes, when one isn't sure about, or one has the feeling, okay, this is probably not coming out of a pressure, the Buddha usually recommend as well, before, while, and after an action by body, speech and mind, to actually keep that context of, okay, you might have started off well, but actually while doing it, you realize the mind takes over, pressures you, and then you actually need to have the capacity to stop yourself in the middle of
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, maybe a project that you really want to finish, but you say, hold on, I'm not going to do this now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that was his advice to his own son.
[SPEAKER_00]: For body, speech and mind, before you're going to do something, question, while you are engaged in those actions, because you see, while being engaged in an action, you can still stop and start doing something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're the one who is acting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then afterwards, you can say, wait, did I not lose perspective?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or maybe it started out right, but somewhere it took a bit of a funny turn.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah, that's useful to have some time at the end of the day to look back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, in particular, like, you know, did I give in to pressure of the own mind or not?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then to determine, well, I need to pay more attention next time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't gain anything from living with a mind that is wild and not trained and tamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because
[SPEAKER_00]: At any moment, anything can happen and you will have to meet that situation with your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the more the mind is opposed to you, the more difficult it will be for you to deal with the situation accurately.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you benefit from living with a mind that is tamed, trained, composed, listening to you, so that you can live your life together, harmoniously, rather than always
[SPEAKER_00]: Needing to fight your own mind and then deal with all sorts of external stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a very poor situation to be in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if things are relatively okay now, you still want to recognize there's no guarantee it's going to stay like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: All sorts of unfortunate situations can happen and then I need to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's going to be much better if I can deal with it with a mind that is there, next to me, than having a mind over against me.